Guide to the Fred Lockley Papers 1839-1958 (bulk 1930-1955) MS 389
New-York Historical Society
Fred Lockley Papers
1839-1958 (bulk 1930-1955)
New-York Historical Society
MS 389
2.6 Linear feet (6 boxes)
This collection documents the career and family life of journalist, author, and rare book dealer Fred Lockley. Much of the material pertains to the history of the Pacific Northwest, and to Oregon, in particular. The Fred Lockley Papers primarily contain correspondence, essays and interviews, and diaries.
Provenance
Numerous donations by Lockley, 1950s.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1871 March 19 Fred Lockley born to Frederic E. Lockley and Elizabeth Metcalf Campbell, Leavenworth, KS.
1895 Lockley receives B.S. from Willamette University, OR.
1897 June 16 Marries Hope Gans, who dies in [1928]. Their children are Frederick Llewelyn, Lawrence Campbell, and Hope.
1900 Lockley works as a postal clerk and for the Nome Nugget newspaper in Nome, Alaska.
1905-1910 Lockley is general manager of Pacific Monthly magazine.
1911 Lockley joins the newspaper the Oregon Journal, where he serves as a columnist into the 1950s.
1917-1918 Serves as a war correspondent in France for the Oregon Journal, New York Herald, and London Globe.
1930 Feb. 19 Marries Laura Simpson.
1958 Lockley dies, [Portland].
Fred Lockley was a journalist and author of numerous books on Oregon and Pacific Northwest history. His columns in the Oregon Journal drew from thousands of interviews of Northwest residents. He also worked as a rare book dealer, specializing in the American West.
See Who's Who in America, 1950-1951, Vol. 26.
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the career and family life of journalist, author, and rare book dealer Fred Lockley. Much of the material pertains to the history of the Pacific Northwest, and to Oregon, in particular. The Fred Lockley Papers primarily contain correspondence, essays and interviews, and diaries. Correspondence includes letters from Lockley's friends, family members, colleagues, and readers; letters and copies of letters from Lockley; and letters between various family members. The bulk of letters concern personal matters, Lockley's columns and publications, rare books and book sales, Western history and reminiscences, and travels. This collection also contains copies of Lockley's essays and interviews with Northwest residents, some of which were presumably published in his column in the Oregon Journal. In addition, several date books for Fred Lockley and his second wife, Laura Simpson Lockley, detail daily life for the couple in the 1930s. The Fred Lockley Papers also contain a small amount of genealogical material, financial records, prints and photographs, ephemera, poetry, clippings, and notes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three major series: Correspondence, Essays and Interviews, and Diaries and Volumes. There are also nine single folder series, including genealogical and family material, financial records, photographs, prints, poetry, ephemera, certificates, clippings, and notes.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence, 1839-1958, undated
Series II: Essays and Interviews, 1919, 1951-1955, undated
Series III: Diaries and Volumes, 1880-1939
Single Folder Series
New York (State) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; California -- Description and travel.; Oregon -- Biography.; New York (State) -- Social life and customs.; Autograph albums; Diaries.; Correspondence.; Schuylerville (N.Y.); London (England) -- History -- Bombardment, 1940-1941.; Metcalf family; Metcalf, Margaret; Simon, Nathan D.; Treadwell, George A.; Vail, R. W. G. (Robert William Glenroie), 1890-1966; Campbell family; Campbell, Elizabeth Metcalf; James, Edith M.; Lockley (Family); Lockley, Elizabeth Campbell; Lockley, Frederick E., 1825-1906; Lockley, Laura Simpson; Lockley, Lawrence Campbell, 1899-1969; Lockley, Maude
- Series I: Correspondence, 1839-1958, undated
  - Subseries 1: Letters to Lockley, 1897-1955
    Scope and Contents note
    This subseries includes letters from Lockley's friends, family members (especially in Montana and Hawaii), colleagues, and readers. Material concerns personal matters, Lockley's columns and publications, rare books and book sales, Western history and reminiscences, and travels. Also included are several letters from Lockley's grandson, Neil Lockley, a sergeant in the Air Force serving in Korea, 1951. A number of items in this subseries are annotated by Lockley.
    - Letters to Lockley, 1897, 1901-1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1917-1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Lockley, from Hawaiian school children, 1952 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters to Lockley, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Lockley, Undated and Fragments (also Alienated Envelopes) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Letters from Lockley, 1882-1955
    This subseries contains letters, and copies of letters, from Lockley to various friends and family members. Topics include travels, rare books, Western history, and the death of Lockley's daughter, Hope, in 1920. Also included are several letters from France in 1918, written while Lockley served as a war correspondent, and two letters written from Nome, Alaska in 1900.
    - Letters from Lockley, 1882-1905 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letters from Lockley, 1910-1918, [1918] (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letters from Lockley, 1920-1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Letters from Lockley, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Lockley, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Lockley, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: Letters between Others, 1839-1955
    Includes letters to and from various family members, including Lockley's mother, grandmother, and sister. Also included are a few letters to and from Lockley's son, Lawrence, and a set of correspondence between Lockley's father, Frederic E., and mother, Elizabeth Campbell.
    - Letters between Others, Frederic E. Lockley and Elizabeth Campbell, 1860-1861 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Letters between Others, 1839-1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 4: Letters between Lockley and R.W.G. Vail, 1944-1958
    Letters between Lockley and R.W.G. Vail, director of The New-York Historical Society, many of which concern donations.
    - Letters between Lockley and Vail, 1944-1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Letters between Lockley and Vail, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letters between Lockley and Vail, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Letters between Lockley and Vail, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letters between Lockley and Vail, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letters between Lockley and Vail--Undated and Alienated Envelopes (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series II: Essays and Interviews, 1919, 1951-1955, undated
  This series primarily contains copies of Lockley's essays and interviews with Northwest residents, some of which were presumably published in his column in the Oregon Journal. Most are untitled and undated. Also included is a draft of Lockley's "Historic Portland," as well as several essays by others, including his son, Lawrence Lockley.
  - "Historic Portland" (1 of 2), Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Historic Portland" (2 of 2), Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Essays and Interviews, 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Essays and Interviews, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Essays by Others, 1919, 1952-1955, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series III: Diaries and Volumes, 1880-1939
  This series contains primarily date books for Fred Lockley and his second wife, Laura Simpson Lockley. Lockley's date books contain lists of books with prices, daily expenses and events. Laura S. Lockley's date books detail daily events. Also included in this series are an autograph book of Lockley's sister, Maude (1880-1883) and a book of telegrams from 1889 congratulating Nathan D. Simon and his wife on their marriage.
  - Fred Lockley: Date Books, 1927, 1934-1935, 1939 (Box 6)
  - Laura Simpson Lockley: Date Books, 1933, 1935-1939 (Box 6)
  - Maude Lockley: Autograph Book, 1880-1883 (Box 6)
  - Nathan D. Simon: Telegram Book, 1889 (Box 6)
- Single Folder Series
  - Series IV. Genealogical and Family Material, 1864-1865, 1891, undated
    This series includes genealogies and notes on family members, Frederic E. Lockley's Civil War military records, and locks of hair.
    - Genealogical and Family Material, 1864-1865, 1891, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Series V. Financial Records, 1862-1952
    This series includes invoices, statements, and stock information. Also included are price lists for books sold by Lockley.
    - Financial Records, 1862-1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Series VI. Photographs, [1892], [1905-1910], undated
    This series includes three portraits of Lockley at various ages, as well as several disparate photographs.
    - Photographs, [1892], [1905-1910], undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Series VII. Prints, Maps, Artifacts, 1876, 1911, undated
    This series includes prints of Oregon sites, a map of South Australia, and a small paper weaving done by Lockley at age five.
    - Prints, Maps, Artifacts, 1876, 1911, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Series VIII. Poetry, undated
    This series contains copies of poetry, from various sources.
    - Poetry, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Series IX. Ephemera, 1919-1954, undated
    This series includes circulars, invitations, direct mail, business and calling cards, membership cards, and tickets.
    - Ephemera, 1919-1954, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Series X. Certificates, 1892-1951
    This series contains military certificates; club, fraternity, and church membership certificates; and certificates documenting library donations. Most items pertain to Lockley.
    - Certificates, 1892-1951 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Series XI. Clippings, 1901-1954
    This series contains newspaper clippings, including copies of Lockley's Oregon Journal column "Lockley's Impressions," and the obituary of Frederic E. Lockley.
    - Clippings, 1901-1954 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Series XII. Notes, Copies, Fragments
    This series contains unidentified and undated notes, and copies of various unrelated documents.
    - Notes, Copies, Fragments, Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)